قرتبة قرية سورية صغيرة وجميلة
Qarataba is a small and beautiful Syrian village.
تقع شرق مدينة عفرين في ريف حلب الشمالي بسبعة كيلومترات
It is located seven kilometers east of Afrin city in the
northern Aleppo countryside.
وتبعد عن الحدود السورية التركية مسافة 30 كيلومتراً
It is 30 kilometers away from the Syrian-Turkish border
باتجاه الجنوب، وتتبع ناحية شران.
towards the south, and belongs to the Sharran sub-district.
إلى الغرب منها تقع قرية قسطل كشك
To its west lies the village of Qastal Kishk.
أما شمالها الشرقي فمزرعة كورتك التابعة لها.
To its northeast is the Kortek farm, which is affiliated
with it.
جنوب غرب القرية تقع قرية عرش قيبار
To the southwest of the village lies the village of Arsh
Qibar.
وأما جنوبها الشرقي فقرية جومكه ومدينة عفرين.
As for its southeast, there is the village of Jomke and the
city of Afrin.
معامل البيرين والصابون وصالات الأفراح
Olive pomace factories, soap factories, and wedding halls
كانت تميز القرية سابقاً
used to distinguish the village in the past,
رغم وجود الزراعة وتربية المواشي كمصدر عيش لأهالي القرية.
despite the presence of agriculture and livestock breeding
as a source of livelihood for its residents.
هاجر قسم من أبنائها لا بأس فيه إلى أوروبا وتركيا
A significant number of its people migrated to Europe and
Turkey
للعمل، ويرسلون مبالغ نقدية إلى أهاليهم في القرية.
for work, and they send money to their families in the
village.
التعليم في القرية متوسط، وقد أنشئت أول مدرسة فيها عام 1970
Education in the village is average. The first school was
established there in 1970,
ثم في الفترة الأخيرة أنشئت مدرسة إعدادية.
and recently, a preparatory school was built.
يشكل المهجرون إلى القرية والمخيمات المحيطة بها
Displaced people in the village and its surrounding camps
نسبة 40% من سكان القرية.
make up 40 percent of the village's population.
يتسم أهلها بطيب المعاملة وحسن المعشر وبساطة الفلاحين.
Its people are characterized by kindness, good
companionship, and the simplicity of farmers.
نحن الآن واقفين بالتحديد فوق تلة قرتبة
We are now standing exactly on top of Qarataba hill,
واللي صايرة في الجهة الشرقية تماماً من قرية قرتبة.
which is located exactly on the eastern side of Qarataba
village.
قرتبة واضحة في أعلى الهضبة بين الغيوم.
Qarataba is clearly visible at the top of the plateau among
the clouds.
التلة، تلة قرتبة، مرتبطة جغرافياً وعسكرياً
The hill, Qarataba hill, is connected geographically and
militarily
بتلتين أخريتين، هي التلة الأولى، تلة كورتك
to two other hills. The first one is Kortek hill,
اللي صايرة بالشرق تماماً أو شرق الشمال،
which is exactly to the east or northeast.
وأيضاً التلة الثانية هي تلة قرية عرش قيبار، عرش قيبار.
And the second hill is the hill of Arsh Qibar village, Arsh
Qibar.
التلتين، أو 3 تلال، مرتبطين مع بعض بالطريق الواصل بين عفرين
وإعزاز.
The two hills, or the 3 hills, are connected by the road
between Afrin and Azaz.
حالياً، يحيط بهذه التلة عدد من المخيمات، واضح تماماً
المخيمات
Currently, this hill is surrounded by a number of camps; the
camps are very visible,
وأيضاً مجرى النهر اللي يأتي من كفر جنة وتشرب منه قرية قرتبة.
as well as the river course coming from Kafr Janna, which
provides drinking water to Qarataba village.
واضح الآن بالكاميرا في جسر، هذا الجسر صاير فوق النهر
You can clearly see a bridge now on camera. This bridge
crosses the river,
قربه كان هناك مطحنة، هذه المطحنة كانت لطحن القمح والحبوب
and near it, there used to be a mill. This mill was for
grinding wheat and grains,
تعمل على المياه، بقوة المياه.
running on water, powered by the water.
أيضاً يحيط بهذه التلة، وهذا الطريق
Also surrounding this hill and this road
عدد من معامل البيرين وأيضاً معامل الصابون وأيضاً صالات
الأفراح
are several olive pomace factories, soap factories, and
wedding halls,
نظراً لقربها من طريق عفرين - إعزاز - حلب، اللي بيودي لحلب
باتجاه الشرق والجنوب.
due to their proximity to the Afrin-Azaz-Aleppo road, which
leads to Aleppo towards the east and south.
حالياً رح نكون معكم لحتى نتوجه لأحد هالمخيمات
Now we will take you to head to one of these camps
ونلتقي سكان أحد الخيم، نتعرف على أوضاعهم الإنسانية
والمعيشية. تفضلوا معنا.
to meet the residents of one of the tents, to learn about
their humanitarian and living conditions. Please come with
us.
يا جماعة!
Hey guys!
يا رب.
Oh Lord. (Come in)
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام.
And upon you be peace.
شلونك؟
How are you?
يا هلا، حياك الله، يا أهلاً وسهلاً، الله يعافيك.
Welcome, may God greet you, welcome, may God give you
health.
برد مو؟
It's cold, right?
إي والله برد.
Yes, by God, it is cold.
سلامتكم.
Stay safe.
حياك الله، الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God greet you, may God keep you safe, Lord.
نتعرف عليك؟
Can we get to know you?
أحمد أبو حسن.
Ahmed Abu Hassan.
يا أهلاً وسهلاً فيك.
You are very welcome.
بيك، الله يعافيك.
Welcome to you, may God give you health.
احكي لي عن هالمخيم هون.
Tell me about this camp here.
احكي لك عن المخيم، نحن من منطقة أبو الظهور، ناحية أبو الظهور
Let me tell you about the camp. We are from the Abu Dhuhur
area, the Abu Dhuhur sub-district.
كل المخيم؟
The entire camp?
إي كلياتنا.
Yes, all of us.
نزحنا، صرنا هون بمنطقة قرتبة شي 3 سنوات تقريباً.
We were displaced, and we've been here in the Qarataba area
for about 3 years.
يعني مجموع سحبتنا 5 سنوات، نزحنا بسراقب بعدين جينا لهون.
I mean, we've been displaced for a total of 5 years. We
displaced to Saraqib, then came here.
كم خيمة فيه؟ كم عيلة؟
How many tents are there? How many families?
تقريباً نحن شي 90 عيلة.
We are approximately 90 families.
90 عيلة.
90 families.
إيش أوضاعكم بالوقت هادا؟
What are your conditions right now?
والله شايف الأجواء برد
Well, you can see the weather is cold.
حالياً، كل مين لابد بخيمته.
Currently, everyone is bundled up in their tents.
وبالنسبة للأوضاع، كل مين عنده شغلة هيك بيشتغلها؟
And regarding the conditions, does everyone have a job they
do?
إيش مشهورين هون أكتر شي؟
What are people mostly known for doing here?
والله حالياً أنا عم بشتغل هون بالزراعة.
Well, currently, I am working here in agriculture.
عم باخد أراضي هيك بستأجر أراضي من هون، من ملاكينها
I'm taking lands, renting lands from here, from their
owners,
وبزرعهم. في ناس عندها أغنام.
and I plant them. There are people who have sheep.
إيش عم تزرعوا؟
What are you planting?
والله حالياً زارعين شعير.
Well currently, we've planted barley.
السنة الماضية زرعت فول هون، وهلق زارع شعير، تيسير الله.
Last year I planted fava beans here, and now I've planted
barley, with God's facilitation.
هذه الأنواع كانت تزرع هون بالأصل، ولا لا تزرع هون؟
Were these types originally planted here, or are they not
usually planted here?
لا، في شي جديد نزل هون، هلق متل الفول جديد
No, some new things were introduced here. Now, things like
fava beans are new.
الحبة السودا جديدة عندهم، يعني هون ما كانوا يزرعوا، كانوا
يزرعوا هنه شعير وحنطة وبس.
Black seed is new to them. I mean, they didn't use to plant
it here; they only planted barley and wheat.
غيرك إيش بيشتغل؟
What do others work in?
في ناس موظفة، عمال يعني.
There are employed people, workers I mean.
وفي ناس عندها غنم.
And there are people who have sheep.
وفي ناس عم تشتغل بمغسل، مثلاً مغسل سيارات وكذا، كل مين حسب
شغلته.
And there are people working at a car wash, for example, a
car wash and so on, everyone according to their job.
أنا جاي شفت حدا قلي إنه هادا المخيم مشهور بأنه الناس بتشتغل
فيه ببيع الألبسة.
When I came, I saw someone who told me that this camp is
famous for people selling clothes.
إي في عنا إي، تمام إي، في عنا 10 عائلات ببيعوا ألبسة.
Yes, we do. Exactly, yes, we have 10 families who sell
clothes.
تقريباً شي 10 - 15 عيلة عندهم سيارات وبيسووا بازار، يعني
ألبسة كامل.
Approximately 10 to 15 families have cars and run bazaars, I
mean a complete clothing business.
متنقلين.
Traveling.
متنقلين إي، كل يوم بمحل شكل، كل يوم مطرح شكل.
Traveling, yes. Every day in a different place, every day in
a different location.
بشكل عام المستوى المعيشي شلون؟
Generally, how is the living standard?
والله منيح، يعني نسبة 50 بالمية كويس، ممتاز.
By God, it's good. I mean, at a rate of 50 percent, it's
good, excellent.
50 بالمية؟
50 percent?
إي، يعني مستورة، مستورة، النسبة التانية.
Yes, I mean it's manageable. It's manageable for the other
half.
طيب، أنتم هون في منطقة يعني كلها فيها معامل
Alright, you are here in an area full of factories,
صابون، بيرين، زيت، و...
soap, pomace, oil, and...
إي نعم. يعني إن شاء الله الأمور منيحة، وأرض زراعية يعني
كمان.
Yes indeed. I mean, God willing, things are good, and
agricultural land too.
ما تكون عمال إي؟
Are there workers?
إي في عنا عمال كمان بيشتغلوا بالمعامل هاي والله.
Yes, we have workers who also work in these factories, by
God.
آه، تكونوا عمال.
Ah, so you work as laborers.
إي في عنا إي، بيشتغلوا.
Yes, we have people who work there.
شلون علاقتكم بالـ... أهل القرية؟
How is your relationship with... the people of the village?
آه القرية، الله يجزاهن الخير والله ما شاء الله كلهم كويسين
ومحترمين.
Ah, the village. May God reward them with good. By God,
Masha'Allah, they are all good and respectful.
واستقبلونا أحلى استقبال والله.
And they gave us the best welcome, by God.
وهنه أمنوا لنا المحلات، يعني وسكنونا فيها هون
They secured places for us, I mean, and settled us in here.
وبيدروا علينا، ناس طيبين كلهم، الحمد لله رب العالمين.
And they check on us. They are all good people, praise be to
God, Lord of the Worlds.
والنعم. إيش إيش هون أنا شايف في وحل كتير، شايف كذا، إيش
الخدمات؟
What a blessing. I see there is a lot of mud here, I see
this... what about the services?
والله هادا متل مانك شايف عينك.
By God, this is as your eyes can see.
يعني ما في حدا خدمنا بالنسبة لموضوع الأرضية.
I mean, no one has provided us with services regarding the
ground condition.
وهادا وضعنا متل مانك شايف عينك والله.
And this is our situation, as your eyes can see, by God.
مي؟ مي كهربا، إشي؟
Water? Water, electricity, anything?
مي إي في منظمة بتيجي بتخدمنا بالمي. كهربا، ألواح طاقة شمسية.
Water, yes, an organization comes and provides us with
water. Electricity, solar panels.
خبز؟
Bread?
خبز، لا ما في.
Bread, no, there isn't.
على حسابكم؟
At your own expense?
طبعاً، على حسابنا منشتري.
Of course, we buy it at our own expense.
احكي لي عن الشخصية إنت.
Tell me about yourself personally.
إيش وضعك إنت؟
What is your situation?
إيش عندك أولاد؟ إيش عندك هيك؟
What children do you have? What do you have?
أنا متزوج من 3 نسوان.
I am married to 3 women.
ما شاء الله.
Masha'Allah.
إي، طبعاً
Yes, of course.
عندي الكبيرة عندها 5 بنات.
I have the eldest wife, she has 5 girls.
والوسطانية عندها 3 بنات وصبي.
And the middle one has 3 girls and a boy.
وهاي الأخرانية جديدة لساتها، 6 - 7 أشهر صارلها، يعني ما
صارلها شي لسه.
And this last one is still new. She's been here 6 to 7
months, so she hasn't had any children yet.
يعني إنت اتزوجت عشان الأولاد؟
So you got married for the sake of having children?
عشان الأولاد إي.
For the sake of children, yes.
سيدي الله يخليلك ياهم.
Sir, may God keep them for you.
الله يسلم عمرك يا رب.
May God protect your life, Lord.
إيش هون في؟ والله هون المضافة، هون الحجي هون كمان قاعد معي
هون.
What is in here? Ah, this is the guest room. The Hajji is
also sitting here with me.
طيب. تفضل تفضل تفضل...
Alright. Please go ahead, go ahead...
يا رب.
Oh Lord.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
وعليكم السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
And upon you be peace, and the mercy of God and His
blessings.
شلونك يا حجي؟
How are you, Hajji?
يا أهلاً وسهلاً بك.
You are very welcome.
شلون صحتك؟
How is your health?
الله يخليك ليا، شلونك إنت؟
May God keep you for me, how are you?
الله يسلمك يا رب.
May God keep you safe, Lord.
الله يخلي لياك ويجبر بخاطرك ويفرج عنك.
May God keep you for me, comfort your heart, and relieve
you.
آمين، آمين يا رب، آمين، آمين.
Amen, amen oh Lord, amen, amen.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته، حياك الله.
Peace and the mercy of God and His blessings, may God greet
you.
خلينا نبرك جنب الحجي.
Let's sit next to the Hajji.
تفضل، تفضل، يا أهلاً وسهلاً.
Go ahead, go ahead, you are very welcome.
شلونك عمو؟
How are you, uncle?
الحمد لله بتلك الأوقات، والفرج من الله والرحمة منه
Praise be to God in these times. Relief and mercy come from
God.
وأنا ماني قاطع الأمل، الله كريم إلا الله يفرجها علينا إن شاء
الله.
And I haven't lost hope. God is generous, God will surely
relieve us, God willing.
إن شاء الله تعالى.
God Almighty willing.
إن شاء الله رب العالمين، الحمد لله رب العالمين، لا
God willing, Lord of the worlds, praise be to God, Lord of
the worlds, no...
نحنا بخير، الحمد لله، والله يفرج علينا وعلى العباد كلها وبس.
We are fine, praise be to God. May God relieve us and all
people, that's all.
آمين. قديش العمر البركة؟
Amen. How old are you, blessing?
يعني، الحقيقة حقيقة، خيو... الحقيقة الحقيقة
I mean, the truth is the truth, brother... the real truth...
أنا الحد مسجل، لإني صار عمري 92. ولكن أكتر من هيك والله
العمري.
I am officially registered as being 92 years old. But by
God, I am older than that.
ما شاء الله، العمر كله.
Masha'Allah, wishing you a full life.
إي، همة ونشاط إن شاء الله.
Yes, determination and energy, God willing.
الحمد لله، قلت لك أنـأنا الحرب العالمية التانية لحقتها
والله.
Praise be to God. I told you that I lived through the Second
World War, by God.
عمري 15 سنة، الحرب العالمية تبعت إيش اسمها الأمم، يعني
لحقتها
I was 15 years old. The World War of the nations, or
whatever it's called, I lived through it.
وحقه لخيو، أنا عمري 15 سنة شب والله.
And he's right to say it, brother. I was a 15-year-old young
man, by God.
إيوا.
I see.
هلق أنا ملاحظ عمو إنه أنتم بهاي الخيمة
Now I am noticing, uncle, that you in this tent...
كأنه أنتو جبتم معكم عاداتكم، تقاليدكم، تراثكم
It's as if you brought with you your customs, your
traditions, your heritage...
ضيافة القهوة المرة... نقلتوها معكم من أبو الظهور لهون، شو
القصة؟
The hospitality of bitter coffee... you brought it with you
from Abu Dhuhur to here. What's the story?
أكيد، سعات اللي متعودين عليها، ما نتركها.
Sure, the things we are used to, we don't abandon them.
أنا أولاً قلت لك يعني ورثت هاي القهوة والمضافة عن أبويا
First of all, I told you, I inherited this coffee and guest
room from my father.
أبويا أخرى عن جدي، ومتعلمين. هادا، هادا عندي النجر هادا تبع
أبويا، طلع هادا
My father got it from my grandfather, and we are raised on
this. This mortar I have is my father's, look at this.
فوق المية سنة عمره هادا.
This is over a hundred years old.
100 سنة؟
100 years?
هادا، هادا هادا، إش نقول له إحنا نجر، مهباش
This, this, this... what do we call it? A mortar, a pestle.
فوق العمر هاي نرجوا... هيك كنا عايشين قلت لك مبسوطين.
It's very old, we pound it... This is how we used to live, I
told you, happy.
الله كان معطينا خيو عنا كان أراضي كتيرة، وعنا، أبويا فوق
الألف دونم يملك
God had given us a lot, brother. We had a lot of lands. My
father owned over a thousand dunams.
وأعمامي إحنا أبويا وأعمامي أربعة إحنا، مالكين ضيعتين
And my uncles... we, my father and my uncles, are four in
total, owning two villages.
كانوا مالكين ضيعتين، يا خيو.
They owned two villages, oh brother.
أراضي كتيرة، وغنم، كنا غنامة أخرى عنا غنم.
A lot of lands, and sheep. We were shepherds too; we had
sheep.
كل واحد عنده 300، 400 راس غنم.
Each one had 300 or 400 heads of sheep.
أبويا وأعمامي. أبويا وأعمامي الأربعة أيضاً
My father and my uncles. My father and my four uncles as
well...
الله كريم، إن شاء الله كل شيء بيرجع.
...
God is generous. God willing, everything will go back to
normal.
نحن يمكن مرتاحين ومبسوطين، ولكن كل شيء حاسين فيه وهيك يصير
فينا نحن حاسين صراحة.
We might be comfortable and happy, but we feel everything,
and what happens to them, we feel it honestly.
إن شاء الله خير.
Hopefully, all will be well.
يا أخي متآمرة علينا، أنا تحليلي وتحقيقي وعقيدتي إنه من 40
سنة 50 سنة دول أوروبية متآمرة على الإسلام وعلى الدول العربية
اللي يصير فيها هيك.
Brother, there is a conspiracy against us. My analysis,
investigation, and belief is that for 40 or 50 years,
European countries have been conspiring against Islam and
the Arab countries for this to happen to them.
عمو حافظان شيء هيك عداوية، شغل ضيعتكم، شغل ديرتكم؟
Uncle, do you know any "Adawiya" (traditional songs),
something from your village or region?
لا ماني حافظان، لا لا ماني حافظان شيء.
No, I haven't memorized any. No, no, I haven't memorized
anything.
بدون ما تغني، بس احكيها حكي.
You don't have to sing, just say the lyrics.
إيش بدي أحكي لك؟ إيش بدي أغني لك؟
What should I tell you? What should I sing for you?
عداوية هيك عن الضيعة، عن المنطقة، عن العشيرة، عن الديرة.
An "Adawiya" about the village, the region, the tribe, or
the homeland.
سلامتك.
Never mind, wishing you health.
والله ماني عارف شو بدي أقول لك، ماني عارف شو بدي أقول لك على
شو...
I swear I don't know what to tell you, I don't know what to
tell you about...
هجين لك هجيني يعني؟
Chant a "Hujaini" (traditional Bedouin poem) for us?
ما أعرف أخوي، ماني عرفان ماني عرفان، والله ماني عرفان.
I don't know brother, I don't know, I swear I don't know.
تسلم، تسلم.
Bless you, bless you.
ماني حافظان بس إنت بدك ما تقول ماني عرفان والله.
I don't know them by heart, but whatever you want me to say,
I don't know, honestly.
الحمد لله رب العالمين، الله يلطف ويفرج عن العالم كلياتنا،
وندعو لله الله يفرج علينا، وكل واحد يرجع على بلاده وعلى بيته
وعلى عالمه.
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds. May God be kind and
bring relief to all people. We pray to God to bring us
relief, and that everyone returns to their country, their
home, and their people.
وإن شاء الله أنا ماني قاطع الأمل من الله أبداً، إلا الله
يفرج علينا.
God willing, I have never lost hope in God, He will bring us
relief.
وإن شاء الله الفرج قريب، أنا متأمل الفرج قريب، الله يفرج
علينا إن شاء الله.
And God willing, relief is near. I am hopeful that relief is
near. May God bring us relief, God willing.
إن شاء الله.
God willing.
الله يعطيكم العافية عمو، شكراً إلكن، شكراً يا أبو محمد، الله
يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health, uncle. Thank you all, thank you Abu
Muhammad. May God give you health.
السلام عليكم.
Peace be upon you.
السلام ورحمة الله وبركاته.
Peace, mercy, and blessings of God be upon you.
شلونكم؟
How are you?
والله الحمد لله بخير، شلونكم؟
Well, thank God, fine. How are you?
نتعرف عليكم؟
Can we get to know you?
أنس الجاسم من ريف حلب الجنوبي، من قرية جزرايا.
Anas Al-Jassem from the southern countryside of Aleppo, from
the village of Jazraya.
أهلاً وسهلاً بيك.
Welcome.
محمد علي الزيدان، من ريف حلب الجنوبي، جزرايا.
Muhammad Ali Al-Zaidan, from the southern countryside of
Aleppo, Jazraya.
أهلاً وسهلاً، شو عم بتساووا هون؟
Welcome. What are you doing here?
والله حداد متنقل.
Well, a mobile blacksmith.
إيه.
Yes.
متنقل.
Mobile.
شلون متنقل يعني؟
What do you mean by mobile?
يعني نشتغل، شو يصير لنا شغل حدادة ببرات عفرين نشتغل. نحن
ساكنين بعفرين وشو يصير لنا شغل حدادة برات عفرين نشتغل.
It means we work, whenever we get blacksmithing work outside
Afrin, we do it. We live in Afrin, and whenever we get
blacksmithing work outside Afrin, we do it.
يعني تتنقلوا بالقرى؟
So you move around the villages?
بالقرى إيوا.
In the villages, yes.
غريب هي، أول مرة بشوف هيك. أنا رح أطفي الموتور شوي...
This is unusual, it's the first time I see this. I will turn
off the generator for a bit...
إحنا كان عنا محل بعفرين، ضلينا 6 أشهر فيه، صار لنا شغل بس
الشغل ضعيف.
We had a shop in Afrin, we stayed in it for 6 months, we had
some work but it was slow.
في شب تعرفنا عليه برات عفرين، والله يجزاه الخير، يعني قام
يعرف علينا عالم كثير.
We met a guy outside Afrin, may God reward him, he started
introducing us to a lot of people.
ومعك معك تعرفت علينا كل العالم.
And little by little, everyone got to know us.
يعني زبون بيجيب زبون؟
So one customer brings another?
إيوا، زبون بيجيب زبون.
Yes, a customer brings a customer.
يا عيني عليك. والحمد لله رب العالمين.
Excellent. And thank God, Lord of the Worlds.
اشتغلتوا بهالضيعة هون؟
Have you worked in this village here?
اشتغلنا بالضيعة هيك صار لنا والله نشتغل فيها شي سنة ونص.
We worked in this village, we've been working here for about
a year and a half.
ما شاء الله.
Mashallah (God willed it).
كل يوم ولا متقطع؟
Yes, honestly.
Every day or intermittently?
لا متقطع.
No, intermittently.
بس داومنا تقريبا فيه شي ثمان شهور شغل كامل يعني، ثمان شهور
متواصلة.
But we worked consistently for about eight months full-time,
eight continuous months.
بعدين صار لنا شغل برات الضيعة صرنا نشتغل، معمل بيرين اشتغلنا
فيه 3 شهور.
Then we got work outside the village, so we started working.
We worked in a pomace factory for 3 months.
والحمد لله رب العالمين، يصير لنا شغل هون نترك، نجي نشتغل،
حسب وين يصير لنا شغل نشتغل.
And praise be to God, when we get work here, we leave and
come to work. We work depending on where we find work.
طيب يعني طالما أنتم جيتوا تشتغلوا، إنتوا هلا وين بتشتغلوا؟
في عندكم هون..؟
Okay, since you came to work, where are you working now? Do
you have something here..?
والله في عنا شغل عند أبو خميس.
Well, we have some work at Abu Khamis's place.
طيب سؤالي، إيش احكوا لي عن الناس اللي هون؟ طبيعة الناس اللي
هون.
Okay, my question is, tell me about the people here? The
nature of the people here.
والله طبيعة الناس كويسين عامة، والحمد لله رب العالمين يعني
متفاهمين معاهم وعالم فيها خير وبركة الحمد لله رب العالمين.
By God, the nature of the people is good in general. And
praise be to God, we have an understanding with them, and
they are good and blessed people, praise be to God.
ويقدرون أمور الناس يعني.
And they are considerate of people's circumstances.
كويس. حضرتك؟
Good. And you sir?
تمام الحمد لله.
Great, thank God.
إيش رأيك في الحكي اللي حكاه الأخ؟
What do you think of what the brother said?
حكي واقعي.
He is speaking the truth.
حكي واقعي؟
Speaking the truth?
أعطيني هيك ميزتين ثلاثة إلهم؟
Yes, honestly.
Give me two or three good traits about them?
كويسين الحمد لله رب العالمين.
They are good people, praise be to God.
طباعهم شلون؟
How are their manners?
تمام.
Great.
تمام؟
Great?
طبعهم كويس الحمد لله رب العالمين، ما شاء الله.
Their manners are good, praise be to God, Mashallah.
طيب هلق وين رايحين؟ لمكان قريب هون؟
Okay, where are you heading now? To a close place here?
والله قريب إي والله.
Yes, it's close by.
يلا بنروح نشوفكم.
Let's go see you work.
يا رب.
Oh God.
شو عم بتساوي هون؟
What are you doing here?
والله عم نساوي درابزين تبع درج.
We're making a handrail for the stairs.
درابزين درج. لك معنا كنت جايب العدة أنت، كنت رايح تجيب العدة
وشفتك أنا.
A stair handrail. You had the tools with you, you were going
to bring the tools and I saw you.
والله كان عندي شغلة برات البيت هذا اللي عم بشتغل فيه، رحت
اشتغلتها واجيت.
I had some work outside this house I'm currently working in,
I went and did it and came back.
هلأ هذا الدرابزين شو شكله؟ موديله؟ كذا؟
Now, this handrail, what is its shape? Its model? Etc.?
هذا، كل شغل، يعني كل ما يصير لنا شغل، نحاول نحدث بشغلنا أكثر
وأكثر.
This, with every job, I mean whenever we get a job, we try
to modernize our work more and more.
إي احكي لي عن هذا التحديث اللي سويته.
Tell me about this modernization you've done.
هذا يتعلق بالدرابزين، الدرج، حطيناله، أول درابزين نشتغله
حطيناله مري، يعني مرايا فيه.
This pertains to the handrail, the stairs. We added... this
is the first handrail we work on where we put mirrors in it.
نعم.
Yes.
يعني المرايا كأنه حديثة أحدث من غيره.
So the mirrors make it seem more modern than others.
في أنواع من هدول؟
Are there different types of these?
في كذا نوع، في عندك مليون نوع بالنسبة للحديد، النوع اللي بدك
ياه تشتغله.
There are several types, you have a million types when it
comes to iron, whatever type you want to work on.
بس ماله مثلاً اسم، ولنفترض هاي، هاي زخرفة نباتية هي؟
But does it have a name for example, let's say this one, is
this a floral pattern?
إي نباتية إي.
Yes, floral, yes.
هاي نباتية، إيش في أنواع تانية؟ وهذا هندسي كمان هون.
This is floral. What other types are there? And this is
geometric here too.
هذا هندسي، إيش بدك تشتغل؟ مثلاً على كيف صاحب البيت.
This is geometric. What do you want to work on? For
instance, it depends on the homeowner's preference.
هين الزلمة اشتغلنا على كيفنا، ما اشتغلنا على كيفه الصراحة.
Here, we worked according to our own taste, we didn't work
according to his, honestly.
ليش على كيفكم؟
Why according to your taste?
على كيفنا نحن، ما يعني هو الزلمة قال يا أخي أنا مسلمكم الشغل
إلكن، واشتغلوا على كيفكن.
According to our taste... well, the man said, "Brother, I'm
entrusting the work to you, work as you see fit."
بالإكراه؟ بالتراضي؟
By force? By mutual consent?
أيوة، بالتراضي طبعاً.
Yes, by mutual consent of course.
بلكي بكرة ما أعطاكم حقكم إذا ما عجبه الشغل؟
What if tomorrow he doesn't pay you your dues if he doesn't
like the work?
بنعيفله ياه عادي، مو مشكلة، هذا صاحب البيت بيستاهل والله.
We would just leave it for him, it's normal, no problem.
This homeowner deserves it, honestly.
هاي دعاية مشان العالم تيجي لعندك؟
Is this an advertisement so people come to you?
أيوة، مشان العالم تيجي لعنا.
Yes, so people come to us.
الله يرزقكم.
May God grant you provision.
الله يسلمك يا رب، والله الحمد لله رب العالمين مشتغلين وما
حدا مقصر معانا يعني، هي الدفعة لحالها بتكفي.
May God keep you safe. Thank God, Lord of the Worlds, we are
working and no one is falling short with us. This push alone
is enough.
الحمد لله رب العالمين، هذا فضل من الله. في غيركم شفت هيك حدا
عنده مهنة، حرفة، يعني بيعرف يشتغل هيك شغل متنقل كمان؟
Praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, this is a grace from
God. Are there others besides you, someone you've seen who
has a profession, a craft, who knows how to do this kind of
mobile work too?
والله ما شفنا.
We haven't seen anyone, honestly.
ما شفتوا، أنتو؟
You haven't seen anyone, only you?
لا. نحن يعني الحمد لله رب العالمين، صار لنا سنة وتقريباً شي
8 شهور نشتغل متنقلين، سنة ونص لـ 8 شهور تقريباً.
No. We, praise be to God, Lord of the Worlds, have been
working mobile for a year and about 8 months. A year and a
half to 8 months roughly.
بس تشتغلوا هالشغلات ولا مثلاً هي ضيعة زراعية، مثلاً ما حدا
بيجيب لك فاس، بيجيب لك سكينة، بيجيب لك...؟
Do you only do these things, or for example, this is an
agricultural village, doesn't anyone bring you a hoe, a
knife, bring you...?
هي على الداير عالراسي هي، هي الفاس وسكاكين شغلة عجيبة هي.
بلطة تبع حطب، كتير، يعني أكتر من سكان البيوت صار عندهم هدول
الشغلات.
This happens constantly. Axes and knives are something
extraordinary. Axes for firewood, a lot, I mean more than
the residents of the houses have these things.
الله يعطيكم العافية، افتحوا الطريق.
May God give you health, clear the way.
الله يعافيك، الله يجزيك الخير يا رب.
May God give you health, may God reward you.
شكراً، عفواً.
Thank you, you're welcome.
بهالضيعة الحلوة، بتضيع التفاصيل بين عرب وبين كرد، في اشتراك
في كل شيء.
In this beautiful village, the details blend between Arabs
and Kurds, there is sharing in everything.
مثل ما في اشتراك بالأعراس والأتراح والأفراح، في أيضاً اشتراك
حتى في المأكولات والمزاج العام.
Just as there is sharing in weddings, sorrows, and joys,
there is also sharing even in food and the general mood.
كولك أو الكولكة، هي أكلة كردية مشهورة كثير في منطقة عفرين.
Kolik or Kolika, is a very famous Kurdish dish in the Afrin
region.
اليوم خالتي إم إبراهيم اللي ساكنة في هذا البيت، راح تفرجينا
كيف تنطبخ وكيف أيضاً تتاكل.
Today, my aunt Um Ibrahim, who lives in this house, will
show us how it is cooked and also how it is eaten.
خلونا ندخل معكم لعند خالتي إم إبراهيم، لنتعرف على مكونات
هالطبخة وكيف تنطبخ، تفضلوا معنا.
Let's go in with you to my aunt Um Ibrahim, to learn about
the ingredients of this dish and how it's cooked. Come with
us.
يا رب.
Oh God.
إم إبراهيم شلونك؟
Um Ibrahim, how are you?
يا رب.
Oh God.
شلونك؟
How are you?
أهلين وسهلين، شلونك شو أخبارك؟
Welcome, how are you, what's your news?
خالتي إم إبراهيم عفوك، أنا بخير.
Aunt Um Ibrahim, excuse me, I am fine.
تفضل، إيه عم نطبخ، إيه.
Come in, yes we are cooking, yes.
يلا.
Let's go.
خالتي إم إبراهيم.
Aunt Um Ibrahim.
يا رب، وين وصلنا؟
Oh God, where did we reach?
يا رب.
Oh God.
الله يعطيك العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
عم تطبخي على النار.
You are cooking on the fire.
إي والله على النار، الجرة غالية.
Yes by God, on the fire, the gas cylinder is expensive.
الجرة غالية مو هيك؟
The cylinder is expensive, isn't it?
إي والله، ما نحسن نجيب جرة غالية.
Yes honestly, we can't afford to buy an expensive cylinder.
هلق إشو هيدي الكولكة؟ احكي لي عن الكولكة؟
Now, what is this Kolika? Tell me about the Kolika?
كولكة هيدي، عدس وبرغل، هيدي نحن هون الكرد يقولوا لها كولكة.
This Kolika, it's lentils and bulgur. Here, the Kurds call
it Kolika.
كولكة.
Kolika.
أيوة، ونحن تعلمناها من الكراد هين، نحن وياهم مو جيران؟ نطبخ
يعني مثل طبخهم، نطبخ بورانية، نطبخ كولكة، هاي طبخات كُردية
هين.
Yes, and we learned it from the Kurds here. Aren't we and
them neighbors? We cook like they cook. We cook Boraniya, we
cook Kolika, these are Kurdish dishes here.
يعني هلق هي الكولكة بتشبه المجدرة؟
So now, is this Kolika similar to Mujaddara?
إي تشبهها، بس لا هيدي هيك بدنا نخلطها هلق نحطها هون على
المي، هيك.
Yes it is similar, but no, this one we have to mix it now,
put it here in the water, like this.
نحطها، نضل نحركها لما تستوي.
We put it in, we keep stirring it until it's cooked.
بتمي تحركيها؟
You keep stirring it?
لا، بس أحركها شوي أول ما أحطها، وبعدين أرجع أكت لها شوية مي
تانية.
No, I just stir it a little bit when I first put it in, and
then I pour a little more water into it.
يعني وأحركها. هلق بدي أعيفها هيك شوي.
And I stir it. Now I want to leave it like this for a bit.
لما يعني تقرب تستوي بعدين...
When it is almost cooked, then...
أرجع أحط لها شوية مي تانية بس.
I'll just add a little more water to it.
شو مكوناتها غير العدس والبرغل؟
What are its ingredients besides lentils and bulgur?
بس، وبصل وفليفلة، بس هدول.
That's it, and onions and peppers, just these.
طيب هي بتصير جامدة ولا بتضل سائلة؟
Okay, does it become thick or does it remain liquid?
لا، جامدة بتصير.
No, it becomes thick.
مو مثل الشوربة؟
Not like soup?
لا، هيديك الشوربة بتضل يعني شوي هيك، بس الكولكة شوي جامدة
يعني بتصير.
No, that soup stays a bit like that, but Kolika becomes a
bit thick.
منتشرة كتير هالأكلة هون؟
Is this dish very widespread here?
إي والله، إي عنا على طول نسويها نحن.
Yes indeed, yes we make it all the time.
أكلة بسيطة؟
A simple dish?
إي إي أكلة بسيطة، والله بس يعني هيك نسويها هي بالأيام يعني.
Yes, yes, a simple dish, really. We just make it like this
during these days.
تكون حدة بالعادي؟
Is it usually spicy?
لك بدها تكون حدة إي.
Of course it has to be spicy, yes.
يعني هون بيحبوا الحد؟
So people here like spicy food?
إي بيحبوا الحد إي والله.
Yes, they like spicy food, honestly.
وكل الناس تحب شكل.
And everyone has their own preference.
كل الناس تحب شكل، الله يعطيكم العافية.
Everyone has their own preference, may God give you health.
الله يعافيك.
May God give you health.
البصلة بتنقلى قلي ولا كيف؟
Are the onions fried or what?
بتقليها بالزيت.
You fry them in oil.
كنا بدنا نخبز، إي ما في عدة، ما ضل عنا عدة، لا طحين ولا هاي
الدفة ولا شي.
We wanted to bake bread, but there are no tools, we have no
tools left, no flour, no baking board, nothing.
سلامتك.
Wishing you health.
يعني بتنفرم، وبتتقلى، وبتنحط ع الوش؟
So they are chopped, fried, and put on top?
أيوة على الوش، بس تستوي بعد ما تستوي.
Yes on top, but only when it's cooked, after it's cooked.
إيش بيتاكل جنبها؟
What is eaten with it?
بيتاكل مكبوس، إذا في مكبوس بيتاكل.
Pickles are eaten with it, if there are pickles, they are
eaten.
لبن كذا؟
Yogurt, etc.?
لبن لا ما بيصير، جنبها ما بيصير، هي ع المكبوس وهيك بصل وبس.
هي أكلة الشتوية هي.
No, yogurt is not suitable, not alongside it. It goes with
pickles and onions, that's it. This is a winter dish.
مو صيفية؟
Not for summer?
هي شتوية حصراً.
It is exclusively a winter dish.
حصراً؟
Exclusively?
إي بس، بس بالشتا نسويها.
Yes, we only make it in the winter.
بالملعقة؟
With a spoon?
إي، أيوة، اللي بده ياكل بالخبز، اللي بده ياكل بالملعقة.
Yes, yes. Whoever wants to eat with bread, or whoever wants
to eat with a spoon.
احكي لي إيش في الأكلات المشهورة هون؟
Tell me, what are the famous dishes here?
والله هي شيشبرك نحن نقوله، كبة، نسوي هيك يعني شغلات والله
يعني مشهورات عنا، الكبة أكتر شي والشيشبرك.
Well, there's Shishbarak as we call it, Kubbah. We make
these things, honestly, they are famous here, Kubbah mostly,
and Shishbarak.
هي الأكلات العربية؟
Are these Arabic dishes?
الكردية، عفواً.
Kurdish, excuse me.
الكردية، إيش الأكلات الكردية؟
Kurdish, what are the Kurdish dishes?
الكردية والله مشكلة كمان يسوون هم، محاشي، يسوون كمان يسوون
كبة، بيسوون يعني هيك كولكة، يسوون بورانية، يسوون هي.
They make a variety of Kurdish dishes too: Mahashi (stuffed
vegetables), they also make Kubbah, they make this Kolika,
they make Boraniya, they make this.
حكيتي بورانية، وحكيتي كولكة، في أكلة تالتة؟
You mentioned Boraniya, and you mentioned Kolika, is there a
third dish?
تفتنا يعني.
We missed it...
تذكرتيهم أنت وكذا أكلة؟
Did you remember them and a few other dishes?
هديك بورانية، إي بورانية.
That one is Boraniya, yes Boraniya.
وإيش كمان؟
And what else?
والله وهي، يعني هيك كولكة وهي يعني.
Well, and this, like Kolika and this one.
هلق أنت شاطرة بإيش، خالتي إم إبراهيم؟
Now, what are you good at, Aunt Um Ibrahim?
والله كل شيء الحمد لله نسوي، يعني كل شيء. نخبز إذا في
طحين...
Well, thank God, we make everything, I mean everything. We
bake bread if there is flour...
إيمتى آخر مرة خبزتي؟
When was the last time you baked bread?
خبزت، من زمان ما عاد صرنا نشتري معدا خبز.
I baked... it's been a long time since we started buying
bread instead.
اشتريتي.
You bought it.
هلق هيدي شو هيدي؟
Now, what is this?
هي دفية نحن.
We call this a "Dafiya".
دفية، يعني؟
A "Dafiya", meaning?
مدفأة خلينا نقول على الحطب.
A heater, let's say, running on firewood.
بتطبخوا هون وكل شيء بتساووه.
You cook here and do everything.
...xwe em hemî nanê xwe vira dipêjin, hemî şixulê me vira
ye.
We cook and do everything.
...xwe em hemî nanê xwe vira dipêjin, hemî şixulê me vira
ye.
...we bake all of our bread here, all of our work is here.
Xwe dipêjin?
You bake it yourselves?
Ê, li ser sacê.
Yes, on the saj.
Li ser sacê? Ê, ma berê tenûr tune bû?
On the saj? Wait, wasn't there a tandoor back then?
Na, em tenûrê nas nakin. Welleh em şixulê ereban nas
nakin... em.. Li ser sacê.
No, we don't know the tandoor. By God we don't know the work
of Arabs...we...on the saj.
Li ser sacê. Welleh eleqeta... Ev ê, ev dar in?
On the saj. By God...these, are these wood?
Ev dar in. Ê.
These are wood. Yes.
Çend zarokê te hene?
How many children do you have?
Ee, elhemdulillah 5 zarokê min hene.
Er, praise be to God, I have 5 children.
5 zarok. Ê, Xwedê ji te re bihêle.
5 children. May God spare them for you.
Xwedê te jî selamet ke. Keçê min tune ne.
May God keep you safe as well. I don't have daughters.
Ma te xema gişkan hilgirtiye.
So you've carried the worry of them all.
Ê welleh ya.. Elhemudlillah, bûkê min jî hene, mîna keçê min
in.
Oh, by God...Praise be to God, I have daughters-in-law as
well, they're like my daughters.
Li ba te rûdinin?
Do they live with you?
Ê, li ba min rûdinin. Gişk li ba min rûdinin, bes yekî
hinekî wisa mala wî dûr e, wî alî ye.
Yes, they live with me. They all live with me, except one
whose house is a bit far, in that direction.
Alîkariya te dikin an bi te re...?
Do they help you or with you...?
Ê, elhemdulillah. Bi min re... Sê heb li vir, bi min re
ne...
Yes, praise be to God. With me...Three of them are here,
with me...
Di heman malê de?
In the same house?
Di heman malê de, ê.
In the same house, yes.
Dipêjin an hûn...?
Do they cook, or do you...?
Na, ew dipêjin, ez. Xwarinê, ez dizanim ez çêdikim, û ew jî
çêdikin. Tiştê ez dizanim çêbikim.
No, they cook, I do. The food, I know what I make, and they
also make it. The things I know how to make.
Bes, yanî tu li ser keyfa xwe, ew li ser keyfa xwe?
So, meaning you do what you want, they do what they want?
Ê ew... Hinek tişt hene ew mîna min nizanin, wisa...
Yeah, they...There are things they don't know like I do,
so...
Aha, wisa ye. Tu muhafeze yî liser turasê.
Ah, so it is. You are preserving the heritage.
Ê ê, welleh ê ê ya hecî welleh.
Yes yes, by God, yes yes pilgrim, by God.
Xwedê we bihêle.
May God spare you.
Xwedê te selamet ke.
May God keep you safe.
Ev çiqas dajo ev?
How long does this take?
Ev welleh dajo, nêzîkî saetekê.
This, by God, takes around an hour.
Saetek.
An hour.
Ê. Dajo, baş dikele, yanî.
Yes. It takes time, boils well, you know.
Xwedê afiyetê bide. Em te li vir bihêlin.
May God give you health. We'll leave you here.
Kerem kin. Na. Bi sihet û xêr.
Go ahead. No. With health and goodness.
Em ê herin û tu bi dilê xwe û rehetî bistirê.
We will go, and you can rest your heart and relax.
Xwedê te selamet ke. Hûn bi xêr hatin.
May God keep you safe. Welcome.
Xwedê te bihêle.
May God spare you.
Mamoste Mihemed, cenabê te, mamosteyî.
Teacher Mihemed, sir, you are a teacher.
Belê.
Yes.
Berê. Û niha jî mamosteyî, li medreseya gund.
Before. And now you are still a teacher, at the village
school.
Belê.
Yes.
Xwedê afiyetê bide we.
May God give you health.
Xwedê te afî ke. Hûn bi xêr hatin.
May God give you health. Welcome.
Rewşa perwerdê çawa ye li vir?
How is the state of education here?
Welleh mamoste, rewşa perwerdê, yanî bi giştî, ji gundên din
cuda nîne.
Well teacher, the state of education, generally speaking, is
not different from other villages.
Em, medreseya me, medreseyeke amadeyî ye.
We, our school, is a preparatory school.
Ji pêşdibistanê heta pola nehan e.
It is from preschool to the ninth grade.
Di medreseya me de heye qederê deh,
In our school, there are about ten,
mamosteyan, di navbera mamosteyên îxtîsasî û mamosteyên
polan de.
teachers, between specialized teachers and classroom
teachers.
Niha di medreseya me de heye derdora, 300 xwendekar.
Right now in our school, there are around 300 students.
Tabi,
Of course,
medreseya me mîna medreseyên din, rastî hin kêmasiyan tê.
our school, like other schools, faces some shortcomings.
Di warê sotemeniyê de,
In terms of fuel,
Carinan em rastî kêmasiya...rûniştgeh, û amadekirinan dibin.
Sometimes we face a lack of...seating, and preparations.
Tu ji rewşa perwerdê çawa dibînî?
How do you view the state of education?
Welleh mamoste, ez tiştekî venaşêrim.
Well teacher, I won't hide anything.
Rewşa perwerdê, ne di asta mebestê de ye. Em hêvî...
The state of education is not at the desired level. We
hope...
Em asta bilindtir hêvî dikin. Lê...
We hope for a higher level. But...
Hewldan têne kirin, yanî, em nikarin mafê hin mamosteyan
înkar bikin.
Efforts are being made, I mean, we can't deny the right of
some teachers.
Yan jî mamoste bi giştî, bi tam taqeta xwe dixebitin lê...
Or teachers in general, work with their full energy, but...
Em hewceyî, rastiyeke baştir in.
We need a better reality.
Yanî, telebeyên qonaxa xwendinê, ya seretayî û amadeyî, hemî
li medreseyê ne?
So, students in the educational stage, primary and
preparatory, are all at the school?
Belê.
Yes.
Li cem we.
With you.
Belê.
Yes.
Li ku didomînin?
Where do they continue?
Niha heta refa nehan e.
Now it is up to the ninth grade.
Piştî nehan, li nehiyeya Şeran. Medreseya sanewiyye.
After the ninth, at the sub-district of Shera. The secondary
school.
Piştî ku xwendina xwe li vir diqedînin, diçin Şeran.
After they finish their studies here, they go to Shera.
Başe.
Okay.
Keç fêr dibin?
Do girls learn?
Ê, belê.
Yes, yes.
Şehadeyên camîeyî cem we hene, ji mêran, yan jî jinan?
Do you have university degrees among you, from men or women?
Ê hene.
Yes, there are.
Bi nîsbeteke baş. Em xwedî îxtîsasin.
At a good rate. We have specialists.
Di felsefê de, di riyaziyatê de, di zimanê erebî de...
In philosophy, in mathematics, in Arabic...
Hin bijîşk hene...
There are some doctors...
Hene...yanî şahadeyên curbecur di gund de.
There are...various degrees in the village.
Temam. Hela madem ku tu ji zarokên gund î,
Perfect. Since you are from the children of the village,
Mirovên wê rewşenbîr in û wiha...
Its people are intellectuals and such...
Tiştekî bala min kişand,
Something caught my attention,
Ku çima qere tepê, yanî bi taybetî,
Why Qere Tepe, meaning specifically,
Meşhûr e bi,
Is famous for,
Sabûnê...Meşhûr e bi senayeta bîrînê, û meşhûr e jî bi...
Soap...It's famous for the olive pomace industry, and it's
famous for...
Fîha, heye li vir meamilên, kargehên kartol û batata û
herwiha,
In it, there are factories here, factories for potatoes and
chips and also,
Meşhûr e...tiştekî balkêş e li salona dawetan.
It's famous...something interesting is the wedding halls.
Fîha, gelek salonên dawetan, wextekî berê. Çi ye qisse? Çi
ye çîrok?
There are many wedding halls, since a long time. What is the
story? What's the tale?
Mamoste, îro,
Teacher, today,
Çi senayet be, lazim e pêsdivî bi maddeyên ewelî heye.
Whatever industry it may be, there is a necessity for raw
materials.
Ya ku senayeta bîrînê teşwîq kir, û bû sedema serkeftina wê.
Ew jî hebûna maddeyên ewelî ye.
What encouraged the pomace industry, and caused its success,
was the presence of raw materials.
Tabi, weke hûn dizanin îro, senayeta bîrînê xwe dispêre
zeytûnan.
Of course, as you know today, the pomace industry relies on
olives.
Mentiqe jî mentiqeyeke zîraî ya dewlemend e bi darên
zeytûnan. Ev emr e,
The region is an agricultural area rich with olive trees.
This matter,
Bû sedema peydabûna senayeta bîrînê,
Led to the emergence of the pomace industry,
Û sabûnê bi heman awayî. Îro...
And soap similarly. Today...
Peydabûna maddeyên ewelî, di serkeftina vê senayetê de
beşdar bû.
The availability of raw materials, participated in the
success of this industry.
Yanî îro,
So today,
Piştî ku berhem didin zeytê arcûn ji meamilên bîrînê.
After they produce the pomace oil from the pomace factories.
Dêvila ku bişînin, cihên dûr, weke mînak li muhazefatên dîn
weke Şamê an...
Instead of sending it, to far places, like for example to
other provinces like Damascus or...
Humis an jî Hemayê,
Homs or Hama,
Ev yek, beşdar bû di peydabûna senayeta sabûnê de.
This one thing, participated in the emergence of the soap
industry.
Çend meamelên bîrînê hene, li vir? Yanî çima mîsalan nebû li
gundên din?
How many pomace factories are there, here? I mean why wasn't
it like this for example in other villages?
Li gund?
In the village?
Li gund û derdora wê de, derdora 5 - 6 meamelên bîrînê hene.
In the village and its surroundings, there are around 5 - 6
pomace factories.
Îlaweyî 6 - 7 mesabina. Yanî...
In addition to 6 - 7 soap factories. So...
Mesabin.
Soap factories.
Ê lakan.
Yes exactly.
Kargehên din, û menaşirên hecer, an jî tiştên wiha?
Other factories, and stone-cutting workshops, or things like
that?
Ê, hene menaşirên hecer. Teqrîben 6 - 7 menaşir hene cem me.
Yes, there are stone-cutting workshops. There are
approximately 6 - 7 workshops with us.
Herwiha meamelê batata,
Also a potato factory,
Cips.
Chips.
Û werşeyat. Werşeyatên xeyatê... Yanî mentiqa...
And workshops. Tailoring workshops... I mean the region...
Yan gund bi taybetî. Tê hejmartin mentiqeyeke zîraî, zêdetir
senayiyê.
Or the village specifically. It is considered an
agricultural area, more than industrial.
Temam.
Perfect.
Senayeta efrah.
The wedding industry.
Yanî, çi ye çîrok ku, çend salên cem we hene? Gelek mezin
bûn.
I mean, what's the story that, how many halls do you have?
They were very big.
El hace.
The need.
Çend salên li cem we hene?
How many halls do you have?
Cem me derdora 4 - 5 salan hene.
We have around 4 - 5 halls.
Pêwîstî, bû sedema peydabûna saleyên efrah. Berê...
Need, led to the emergence of wedding halls. In the past...
Mentiqe bi giştî. Yên ku dawetên xwe dikirin, diçûn Helebê.
The region in general. Those who held their weddings, used
to go to Aleppo.
Jiber, dûrbûna mesafê, û...
Because of, the distance, and...
Tekalîfa.
The costs.
Û zehmetî.
And the difficulty.
Ku dizanin emrê, bişînin teqrîben derdora 60 - 70 kîlometre.
Knowing the task, to send them approximately 60 - 70
kilometers.
Pêwîstî bû sedemê derketina, saleyên efrah.
Necessity led to the emergence, of wedding halls.
Hela bi min pisyareke dawî maye tenê, yanî. Ez,
Now I have just one final question remaining, really. I,
Têbîr dikim.
Am expressing it.
Û min bihist ku dema ku min ev bername amade dikir.
And I heard that when I was preparing this program.
Ku qey xanek cem we hebû.
That supposedly you had an inn.
Li, ketina gund de ji hêla rêya Ezaz - Efrîn.
At, the entrance of the village from the direction of the
Azaz - Afrin road.
Belê.
Yes.
Û herwiha hebû pira. Ev pira, pira...
And also there was the bridge. This bridge, the bridge...
Yanî, reka di ser wê re derbas dibû, rêya kevin.
I mean, the road that crossed over it, the old road.
Ji min re li ser wan herduyan qala bike.
Tell me about both of them.
Mamoste, ev xan, kevn e. Ne gihaye me
îla...îbareta...rîwayetan e.
Teacher, this inn, is old. It didn't reach us except...just
as...tales.
Çi ye navê wî bû?
What was its name?
Mehelî, tê nasîn bi Xan Berî Moxle.
Locally, it is known as Xan Berî Moxle.
Ew aniha,
That one now,
Tune ye, ev xan. Înnema,
Doesn't exist, this inn. But,
Îbareta measireyek, li ser bermahiyên xanê hatiye çêkirin.
It is just a press, built on the ruins of the inn.
Belê.
Yes.
Fa, ev xan berê,
So, this inn in the past,
Ji me re qal dikin dapîr - bapîrên me.
Our ancestors tell us about it.
Ku hebû li vir, ji tenişta gund re derbas dibû, rêya
hevrîşim.
That it was here, passing by the side of the village, the
Silk Road.
Di rêya hevrîşim a dewletî.
On the international Silk Road.
Fa...
So...
Li ser wê rêyê hat dîtin.
It was found on that road.
Ev xan. Ji bo bêhnvedana qawafilan. Mirovan rehetî digirtin
li ser vî rêyî.
This inn. For the resting of the caravans. People took rest
on this road.
Fa,
So,
Ev xan hat dîtin. Û ta niha,
This inn was found. And until now,
Hin asarê wî heye, niha lê belê,
It has some traces, now but,
Lê tune bûn, liser xaleb.
But they were destroyed, for the most part.
Û pirr?
And the bridge?
Pirr qedîm e.
The bridge is ancient.
Ew li ser nahr e tê ji Kefercenê.
It is over the river coming from Kefercene.
Tabi, ev nahr di alî gund de derbas dibe, ev nahr Kefercenê
ye.
Of course, this river passes through the side of the
village, this river is Kefercene.
Pirr, bi wê tê naskirin navê wî pira Awec.
The bridge, is known by that name, the Awec bridge.
Ev pira,
This bridge,
Dîroka wê kevn e, divegere bo dema Osmaniyan. An jî qeblî
wî.
Its history is old, it dates back to the Ottoman era. Or
even before that.
Ev pira niha,
This bridge right now,
Hêj niha heye.
Still exists today.
Û berê,
And in the past,
Erebeyan li ser wê derbas dibûn. Bi şeklekî multex, liser vî
pirr. Ji ber wê navê wê kirin pirra Awec.
Vehicles used to pass over it. In a twisting way, over this
bridge. That's why they named it the Awec (crooked) bridge.
Kûi qesî.
A sharp bend.
Kûi. Belê.
Bend. Yes.
Haliyan, pirr.
Currently, the bridge.
Xeyr...yanî salikî li ser morora erebeyan.
Is not...meaning passible for the passage of cars.
Hat avakirin, pireke nû. Ev pirr dihat bi karanîn ji bo
erebeyan.
A new bridge, was built. This bridge was used for cars.
Rêya înzah ji ser pirê?
Was the road moved away from the bridge?
Înzah, belê belê. Pira qedîm xeyr di karanînê e niha.
Moved, yes yes. The old bridge is out of use now.
Şukren mamoste Mihemed.
Thank you teacher Mihemed.
Miye selame.
A hundred greetings.
Meilûmatin qeyme û maşaelleh ser te.
Valuable information, and God bless you.
Şereftu mamoste. Ehla wesehla te şeref da, sed silav.
You honored me teacher. Welcome, you brought honor, a
hundred greetings.
Tebîeta cuxrafya, û nematê întac, û nematê heyat, bi vê
gundê,
The nature of geography, and the pattern of production, and
the pattern of life, in this village,
Basîta,
The simple one,
Fered halê, bi şeklekî mezin, liser,
Imposed itself, in a big way, on,
Floklora xînayî,
The singing folklore,
Floklora xînayî a şa'bî,
The popular singing folklore,
Li gundê qeretepê, û eyden liser.
In the village of Qere Tepe, and also on.
Ziyiyê, şa'bî a teqlîdî a libasê, swaend endê rîcal an jî
ensa.
The popular traditional attire of clothing, whether for men
or women.
Em ê behs bikin, şwiyê li ser, floklora şa'bî,
We will talk, a bit about, the popular folklore,
Bi vê mentiqê em ê biaxivin bi em,
In this region, we will speak with the uncle,
Necm Ebû Hesen. Ellî huwwe, yek...
Necm Ebu Hesen. The one who is, one...
Ku...bi xwedikirin...xenem, ji zeman.
Who...were raising...sheep, since a long time ago.
Umrê wî bi tecawiz maşelleh, foqet tîmenînê sennê.
His age exceeds, praise be to God, over eighty years.
Xwedê jêre sihet û afiyetê bide.
May God grant him health and well-being.
Û bi sebebê tebîeta emelê,
And due to the nature of work,
Di terbiyeta heywanan, û re'î, û teraqul wera eha, û ziraê,
In raising animals, and herding, and moving behind them, and
agriculture,
Huwe hafizan,
He is a memorizer,
Fîlen huwe xezaneta a floklora şa'bî fî qeryetê qeretebê.
Truly he is a treasury of the popular folklore in the
village of Qere Tepe.
Emî Ebû Hesen, Xwedê afiyetê bide.
Uncle Ebu Hesen, may God give you health.
Xwedê te jî afî bike.
May God give you health too.
El emr qedeş lî bereke?
The age, how much is the blessing?
Welleh.
By God.
Foqî 80
Over 80
Maşelleh, maşelleh.
Praise be to God, praise be to God.
Ez mîna min got tu hevzan koli şî hûn bi folklôr şaabî...
As I said you know everything here in the popular
folklore...
Neam.
Yes.
Xenî, kolê enwei xanim.
Rich, all the types of singing.
Neam.
Yes.
Û tu bûyî şêxê şebaban û tebolan.
And you were the master of youth and drums.
Neam.
Yes.
Di dawetan de, li byadir,
In the weddings, at the threshing floors,
Û te hiştinê tune minne k temro.
And you left no occasion to pass.
Neam.
Yes.
Ji min re bibêje enwaiya xîna li vira, şûn tixenin hon, bi
qeryatê qeretebê?
Tell me the types of singing here, what do they sing here,
in the village of Qere Tepe?
Welleh tiştek xînayên, hay itabê.
Well some singings, this ataba.
Swêhlî, Nêl, hîya,
Swehli, Nail, this,
Erebî ewwelî, heza xînayê hon.
Old Arabic, this is the singing here.
Ataba?
Î, Nêl, Swêhlî.
Yes, Nail, Swehli.
Bês.
Just that.
Bes hezûlih.
Just those.
Teyib etinî mîsel eli kol wahdî,
Okay give me an example of each one,
Meberef mîsel şu.
I don't know an example of what.
Ewwelî ken şikil heleq şikil.
In the past it was a way now it's a way.
Ewwelî ken heza xinenê ya nî, heza el medlub heşkî hez...bi
ares, bi tbul, bi zmûr.
In the past this was our singing I mean, this was what was
requested like this...in weddings, with drums, with zurnas.
Hazal rîna yanî.
This was the singing I mean.
Ey teyb ewwelê şukuntet xenno, hez li şof atina nail wa
tluba.
Yes okay in the past what were you singing, let's see give
us a nail and a tluba.
Hez etaba.
This ataba.
Sameanî?
Let me hear?
Hêse ettek sammekî yah.
Now I will let you hear it.
Halleq bestnî sor.
Now just wait for me to take a picture.
Um.
Qul regêt bi ras eylî, tintşrif elîhom û dam a eleyn may
inşif elîhom.
Say I climbed to a high peak, to look over them and the
tears of the eye don't dry for them.
Ebû bel rîh selomlî aleyhom adet may moclek işeb bi xele.
O blowing wind send them my greetings, numbering the waves
of grass in the void.
Hey elatebe.
This is the ataba.
Mafiq txaniya?
Can't you sing it?
Le, nefesê may tilal.
No, my breath doesn't come out.
Şuwy bes bi sita may.
A little just a simple way.
Wela wela.
No no.
Mşen lî muşhedin.
For the viewers.
Ya xay alal ismeh welleh maytilai, ma yitlali, nefesê
matile.
Oh brother about hearing, by God it doesn't come out, it
doesn't come out for me, my breath doesn't come out.
Teyb teyb tinê nêl.
Okay okay give us a nail.
Nêl.
Nail.
Nêl deleyil feqer mo delyil xeyr.
Nail is a sign of poverty not a sign of goodness.
Qite btûn lî ziml, xiser zhor el xêl.
It cut the bellies of camels, broke the backs of horses.
Heza Nêl.
This is Nail.
Mîni heyl amtahkê enit.
Who are you talking about.
Neam?
Yes?
Btqul qeta zhor.
You say cut the backs.
El xêl.. Ê min hez lî qeta zhor...
The horses...Yes this is what cut the backs...
Xêl...nêl. Nêl heza.
Horses...Nail. This is Nail.
Neam...Yiqul nêl delayl feqer.. Mû delayl xêr yani.
Yes...It says nail is a sign of poverty.. Not a sign of
goodness I mean.
Naam...î qette a bton e zml, keser zohur exêl.
Yes...yes it cut the bellies of the camels, broke the backs
of the horses.
Qettea btton iziml ele bear...
It cut the bellies of camels, which are the bears
(camels)...
Beîr...
Camel...
Cîmel..ê...
Camel..yes...
Neam...
Yes...
Mibedû, ishwêhlî...
After it, the swehli...
Swhêlî..
Swehli..
Ishwêhlî.
Swehli.
Şerecye helbas, şerce zhert aawad. Şeybeyi yahal raes
wanseyibt mocayêb...
Sharjiye is this clothes, sharjiye appeared O Awad. Greying
of this head and if you grey it's no surprise...
Eny...ehzya ishêhlî.
I mean...this is the swehli.
Şhêhlî.
Swehli.
Ê haza swêhlî.
Yes this is swehli.
Aamtiktesre ketr, lîyş?
You are shortening it a lot, why?
Emmma...nefîssy maytlea...
But...my breath doesn't come out...
عمال يشتغل نفسي، خلص صرت ختيار.
My breathing is heavy, I've become an old man.
إنت شب لساك يا عمي.
You are still a young man, Uncle.
لا لا، ماني شب.
No, no, I am not young.
حسب ما فهمت تمشي عشرة كيلو متر كل نهار وأكثر؟
As far as I understand, you walk ten kilometers every day or
more?
المشي هين علي، بس النفس صار صعب.
Walking is easy for me, but breathing has become difficult.
سلامتك.
I hope you feel better.
الله يسلمك.
May God keep you safe.
إيمتى بيتغنى كل واحد من هدول؟ النايل والسويحلي والعتابا.
When is each of these sung? The Nayil, the Sweihli, and the
Ataba?
والله هدول حسب الطرب يعني، حسب إنه ما يريد الزمان.
Well, these depend on the mood, meaning, depending on what
the moment calls for.
هلق جينا مثلاً على عرس..
For example, if we come to a wedding...
وبدك ناس تغني وناس ترقص وناس تصفق، كل ناس شكل يعني.
And you want people to sing, people to dance, and people to
clap... everyone does something different.
والسلطنة على إيش؟
And what brings on the true "Saltana" (musical ecstasy)?
السلطنة عالدبك وعالغناء.
The Saltana is in the dabke and the singing.
الغناء قصدي العتابا ولا النايل ولا السويحلي؟
By singing, do you mean Ataba, Nayil, or Sweihli?
لا العتابا.
No, the Ataba.
إي.
The Ataba has Saltana?
Yes.
والرقص؟
And the dancing?
الرقص كل واحد يعرف يرقص هو الرقّيص.
Dancing, everyone who knows how to dance is a dancer.
ع السويحلي؟
To the Sweihli?
إي لا ع السويحلي، ع الطبل ع ال.. هيك شيء يعني.. كلياته. بس.
Yes, no, to the Sweihli, to the drum, to... things like
that... all of it. That's it.
أحب شيء إلك بحياتك شو هو؟
What is the thing you love most in your life?
والله أحب شيء إلي، ما شفت من حياتي شيء، يعني دوم بالغنم
وبالجول.
Honestly, the thing I love most... I haven't seen much of
life, I've always been with the sheep and in the wilderness.
ما شفت من حياتي شيء قليل قليل.
I haven't seen much of my life, very little.
قصدك ما تنعمت، ما ترفهت؟
You mean you didn't enjoy luxury, you didn't live
comfortably?
لا، هيك ما صار لي، ما طلع لي شيء أترفه بيه.
No, I didn't get that, I didn't get a chance to live
comfortably.
بتحب الغنم؟
Do you love the sheep?
إي أحبها.
Yes, I love them.
ليش؟
Why?
ربيت معاها، مني عجي مثل الأولاد هدول، مع الغنم، لا زال.
I grew up with them, since I was a child like these kids,
with the sheep, until now.
وما زلت؟
And you still do?
وفية الغنم مو هيك؟
Yes.
Sheep are loyal, right?
لا وفية وتأنس وما فيها.. مالهاش شكل غلط.
Yes, loyal and comforting, and there's nothing wrong with
them at all.
ليش بيسموها منايح؟ أو منيحة؟
Why do they call them "Manayih" (beneficial ones) or
"Mneeha"?
منيحة إنه هاليوم مثلاً عندك منيحة خمس ست غنمات عشرة..
Mneeha because today, for example, you have a "mneeha" of
five, six, or ten sheep...
تاكل منهم حليب، تاكل منهم سمن، تاكل منهم لبن، تاكل.. هاي
منيحة.
You consume their milk, you consume their ghee, you consume
their yogurt, you consume... that's why they are "mneeha".
يعني هن بركة.
Meaning they are a blessing.
إي، وإذا يجيك مثلاً 50 ضيف، تذبح خاروف يوفي مع الكل.
Yes, and if you get, for example, 50 guests, you slaughter a
sheep and it's enough for everyone.
الله يقويك ويطول عمرك.
May God give you strength and a long life.
الله يسلمك ويخليك ويكثر أمثالك.
May God keep you safe, protect you, and multiply people like
you.
الله يحفظك، بدي أسأل عمي أبو إبراهيم.
May God protect you. I want to ask Uncle Abu Ibrahim.
أهلاً.
Welcome.
أنا ملاحظ إنه الآن إنت..
I notice that right now, you...
أبو إبراهيم، أبو حسن، وأيضاً عمي أبو محمد.
Yes.
Abu Ibrahim, Abu Hasan, and also Uncle Abu Muhammad.
هذا ابن عمي، وهذا ابن أختي.
This is my cousin, and this is my sister's son.
والنعم، والنعم.
Nice to meet you, nice to meet you.
نفس الزي التقليدي لابسينه؟
Are you wearing the same traditional outfit?
إي نفس التقليدي.
Yes, the same traditional one.
إيش هو؟ احكي لي إيش هو الزي التقليدي اللي هون؟
What is it? Tell me, what is the traditional outfit here?
هذا زي يعني زينا كلياتنا نلبس هاللباس، اللي بده يلبس..
الآدمي الكبير..
This is an outfit... meaning, it's our outfit, we all wear
these clothes. Whoever wants to wear... the older men...
بده يلبس يعني لباس مثل ما يقولوا يعني، يلبس بريم، يلبس
جمدانة أو مركزيت..
He wears, meaning, clothes as they say, he wears a brim
(cord), he wears a jamdana (headscarf) or markazite (white
headscarf)...
جلابية، هذا لباسنا يعني زينا.
A jalabiya, these are our clothes, I mean, our outfit.
كأنه اللي.. كلهم جمدانة حمرا، ما في بيضا؟
It seems that... all of them are wearing a red jamdana, are
there no white ones?
اللي بده يلبس بيضا يلبس.
Whoever wants to wear a white one, can wear it.
بس الأكثر حمرا؟
But the majority are red?
الأكثر هالحز طلعت الجمدانة الحمرا، أولي ما فيه جمدانة حمرا..
The majority right now is the red jamdana, in the past,
there was no red jamdana...
ما يصنعونهن، كان المركزيت الأبيض يلبسون المركزيت، إي.
They didn't manufacture them, it was the white markazite,
they used to wear the markazite, yes.
طيب وأنتم واضعين بهاي الطريقة هيدي إنت حاططها بتلفها هيك..
And you are wearing it in this way, you put it on and wrap
it like this...
هذا تراث، هذا فلكلور عندكم تلفوها هيك؟
Is this a tradition, is this folklore for you to wrap it
like this?
إي هيك يعني، بي ناس تردها هيك، بي ناس تسويها هيك، هالحز أنا
هيك سويتها.
Yes, like this, meaning, some people fold it back like this,
some people do it like this. Right now, I did it like this.
هيك اللباس عاد.. بي كل واحد حسب رأيه.
This is how the clothes are worn... everyone does it
according to their preference.
اليوم الشباب اللي عمرهم 30-40 سنة بيحطوا؟
Today, do young men who are 30-40 years old wear it?
لا.. ما عاد يلبسون.
No... they don't wear it anymore.
صاروا يلبسوا قبع، يلبسوا لفاحة.
They started wearing beanies, they wear scarves.
طيب النسوان إيش بيلبسوا هون؟
Well, what do the women wear here?
النسوان أولي، شكل، النسوان القديمة كانوا يلبسوا مركزيت..
Women in the past, were different. Older women used to wear
markazite...
محرمة بيضا، وعصبة سودا..
A white scarf, and a black headband...
فوقها؟
On top of it?
إي، أو شطفة.
Yes, or a shatfa (a type of headband).
إي شطفة، عصبة شطفة.
Yes, a shatfa, a shatfa headband.
إي إحنا نقول لها عند العرب شطفة، إي.
Yes, we call it "shatfa" among the Arabs, yes.
ويلبسن لقلق ويلبسن ثوب أو جلابية.
And they wear a luqluq (traditional baggy trousers) and a
dress or jalabiya.
وحالياً؟
And currently?
حالياً صار كل واحد يلبس شكل، ما ظل زي.
Currently, everyone wears different things, there is no
single outfit left.
هاي لابس بنطلون، هذا لابس جلابية، هذا.. ما ظل زي واحد.
This one is wearing trousers, this one is wearing a
jalabiya, this one... there is no uniform outfit anymore.
بس إحنا الكبار، مثل أبو حسن، مثل أبو محمد..
But we, the older men, like Abu Hasan, like Abu Muhammad...
نلبس بريم، إذا بدنا نروح مثلاً على تعزية، نروح على فرح،
نروح..
We wear a brim (cord), if we want to go, for example, to a
condolence gathering, go to a wedding, go...
نلبس لباس، جلابية وبريم أو فروة، هذا لباسنا.
We wear our clothes, a jalabiya and a brim, or a farwa (fur
coat), this is our outfit.
اللباس الرسمي اللي بيعطي خلينا نقول يعني وجاهة؟
The formal attire that gives, let's say, prestige?
أيوة هذا.
Yes, this one.
إي هذا لباسنا.
It gives him an imposing presence?
Yes, this is our outfit.
خليني أروح لعند عمي أبو محمد.
Let me go to Uncle Abu Muhammad.
تفضل.
Go ahead.
عمي أبو محمد، إنت يعني عاصرت الفترتين، القديمة اللي عم يحكي
عليها أبو إبراهيم..
Uncle Abu Muhammad, you have lived through both periods, the
old one that Abu Ibrahim is talking about...
والفترة الحالية، فترة الشباب والتطور والزحمة ووجع الراس.
And the current period, the period of youth, development,
crowding, and headaches.
نعم.
Yes.
احكي لي إيش شفت يعني بالفترتين، أيا هي أحب إلى قلبك؟
Tell me what you have seen in these two periods, which one
is closer to your heart?
والله أولاً أهلاً وسهلاً بكم، مية سلامة شرفتونا.
Well, first of all, welcome, a hundred greetings, you have
honored us.
يا هلا بيك.
Welcome to you too.
الله يخليك.
May God bless you.
والله يا أخوي أبو عبدو إحنا.. عاداتنا وتقاليدنا..
Honestly, my brother Abu Abdo, we... our customs and
traditions...
بالنسبة للأعراس وللتعزية، عندنا تعزية يعني..
Regarding weddings and condolences, for condolences, we
have...
بعيد من هين، أهل الميت يعني 3 أيام ما يطبخوا.
God forbid, the family of the deceased, meaning, they don't
cook for 3 days.
الجيران يعني، جيرانه يعني.. اليوم الغدا عند فلان، اليوم عند
فلان، اليوم عند فلان..
The neighbors, I mean, his neighbors... today lunch is at
so-and-so's, today is at so-and-so's, today is at so-and-
so's...
هاي العادات يعني، تقاليدنا. والأعراس..
These are the customs, our traditions. And weddings...
زاد مشترك..
Also shared...
إي. بي مريض بدنا نزوره، كلياتنا نروح..
Yes. If there is a sick person we need to visit, we all
go...
مثل الشيخ خليل وغيره، والشباب كلها مثل ما أقول..
Like Sheikh Khalil and others, and the young men all, as I
say...
فلان مرضان تفضلوا تنروح نزوره.
So-and-so is sick, please let's go visit him.
إي، وهاي عاداتنا وتقاليدنا، يعني.
Yes, and these are our customs and traditions, you see.
إحنا باركين الآن في غرفة صغيرة ململمة شوي، الجو برا بارد
كتير..
We are sitting now in a small, somewhat cozy room. The
weather outside is very cold...
وعم ينزل مطر شوي، لكن هون في دفا.
And it's raining a little, but here it is warm.
السقف أنا شايفه خشب.
The ceiling, I see, is made of wood.
طيب، يعني هذا النمط، هذا النمط من البيوت، بناء البيوت، هذا
هو كان الغالب في الضيعة؟
Yes.
طيب، يعني هذا النمط، هذا النمط من البيوت، بناء البيوت، هذا
هو كان الغالب في الضيعة؟
So, meaning, this style, this style of houses, building
houses, was this the predominant style in the village?
هذا يعني الدار، القديم.. إحنا نقول لها دار.
This, meaning the house, the old one... we call it "dar"
(house).
اللي هيك عنده دار مرتبة، يجيب لها مثل ما يقول غرف للضيوف
يعني..
Whoever has a well-arranged house like this, brings to it,
as they say, rooms for guests, I mean...
يحط دف، عمد بالاول، فوقهن دف، وفوق الدف تراب.
He puts wooden boards, pillars first, above them wooden
boards, and above the boards, dirt.
وبعد التراب كم كيس إسمنت يعني، كم كيس شمنتو، مشان المي.
And after the dirt, a few bags of cement, I mean, a few bags
of cement, for the water (to prevent leaking).
أولي، قبل الشمنتو يطلون وحل يعني..
In the past, before cement, they used to coat it with mud...
وحل.
Mud.
طين وتبن ووحل، إي.
Mud, straw, and wet earth, yes.
في كل بيت غرفة وحدة بس؟ غرفة ضيوف؟
In every house, is there only one room? A guest room?
إي هاي غرفة ضيوف هاي مثل هاي، هاي أثرية قديمة.
Yes, this is a guest room, like this one. This is an old
heritage one.
وهيدي حلوة ما زلتوا محافظين عليها.
And this is beautiful, you have still preserved it.
إي محافظين، ومثل ما تفضلت أولي أهالينا كانوا ببيوت شعر،
وغنامة، ولا زال الغنم..
Yes, preserved, and as you mentioned, in the past, our
families lived in hair tents (Bedouin tents), as sheep
herders, and the sheep are still...
بيت الشعر أطيب ولا الغرفة القديمة هيدي؟
Is the hair tent better or this old room?
والله أنا ما وعيت.. يعني وعيت ببيت الشعر بس ما سكنت بيه.
To be honest, I didn't experience... I mean, I was aware of
the hair tent, but I didn't live in it.
إي من خلقت بهالبيوت هدول الدور يعني، بس أهلنا يحكولنا
قديماً.
You didn't live in it?
إي من خلقت بهالبيوت هدول الدور يعني، بس أهلنا يحكولنا
قديماً.
Yes, since I was born, it was in these houses, these "dour",
I mean, but our parents told us about the old days.
الله يعطيكم العافية.
May God give you health.
الله يعافيك يا رب.
May God give you health too.
شكرا لكم عمي أبو محمد، شكرا عمي أبو حسن، وعمي أبو إبراهيم،
شكرا لكم.
Thank you Uncle Abu Muhammad, thank you Uncle Abu Hasan, and
Uncle Abu Ibrahim. Thank you.
أهلاً وسهلاً، شرفتوا ومية أهلاً وسهلاً بكم جميعاً، الله
يحييك.
You are welcome, you have honored us, and a hundred welcomes
to all of you, may God bless you.